Guide to the Michael Joseph Williams notebooks, 1978-1990
Williams, Michael Joseph notebooks, 1978-1990
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Michael Williams notebooks, 1978-1990
7444
Michael Joseph Williams, 1958-1991
.7 cubic ft.
Notebooks astrological charts, calendars,correspondence,postcards,poems,photographs
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Notebooks kept by Williams from 28 December 1980 to 8 May 1990. Comprised of diary entries, astrological charts, calendars, outgoing and incoming correspondence, postcards, poems, photographs, tickets, programs, and invitations.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Michael J. Williams was born in Virginia on 4 February 1958. After graduating from San Francisco State University in 1985, he took a Masters degree from the University of California at Davis. He was chair of the Gay Rights Chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union of Northern California. Williams died of AIDS related causes on 23 April 1991.
The collection consists entirely of notebooks kept by Williams from 28 December 1980 through 8 May 1990, and is comprised of diary entries, astrological charts, calendars, outgoing and incoming correspondence, postcards, poems, photographs, lists, and such pieces of attached ephemera as tickets, programs, and invitations. The latter notebooks have few diary entries, and consist chiefly of correspondence, calendars, and postcards.
The diary entries and correspondence feature Williams' reflections on and expressions of gay life and love, his work in and doubts about graduate school, his love of nature and care for the natural environment, and his attention to friendships and family relations. A principal topic of the notebooks and the diaries is AIDS and the effects of the disease on his friends and in the gay community. There are several AIDS death notices in the notebooks. The notebooks chronicle Williams' coping with the AIDS related illnesses and death of his lover Mike Kurtz, and include Williams' thoughts on the disease. As he has elsewhere apostrophized the moon in letters in his diary, Williams also addresses Kurtz some time after the latter's death. After his own contraction and treatment of the disease, Williams describes the effects on his life of testing positive for HIV, .... He participated in the University of California at San Francisco's AIDS Behavioral Research Project, and the Palo Alto Medical Foundation's Study of the Costs of AIDS Patients.
Throughout the notebooks, his family is sympathetic, especially his father and his sister; his chief correspondent is a woman who was his first girlfriend. Williams' infatuation with a man named Tony is also chronicled in letters to and from the subject, and in diary entries. Williams' concerns with the moon and its influence on him are carefully noted, both in prose and in detailed charts. He is addressed in several pieces of correspondence as Wander-Moon, or Wander, Wander, and Wanda-Luna.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Notebooks consisting of diary entries, incoming and outgoing correspondence, astrological charts, photographs, postcards, and ephemera dealing with homosexuality, graduate school, astrology, romantic affairs, AIDS and its effects on the gay community, the death of Williams' lover, Mike Kurtz, of AIDS related illnesses, and Williams' own experiences testing positive for HIV and coping with AIDS.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Williams, Michael Joseph, 1958-1991.
Subjects:
AIDS--Disease.; Gay men.; Homosexuality--Male.; Moon--Influence on man.; Astrology.
Form and Genre Terms:
Notebooks.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Notebooks
Boxes 1-2
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Notebooks
  - Winter 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Spring 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Summer 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Late Summer 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fall 1981 (Part I) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fall 1981 (Part II) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Winter Vacation 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Spring/Summer 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fall 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Spring 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - May 1983-March 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - March 1984-August 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fall 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1986 Begins (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Summer 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fall 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1987 Begins (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Enter #29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Spring 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Summer 1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [Death of Mike Kurtz] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1987 Ends (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1988 Begins (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Spring 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Thesis I (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Thesis II (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Life after Grad School (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Christmas 1988-April 1989 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - May-August 1989 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - September 1989-November 1989 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Novemer 1989-February 1990 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - February 1990-May 1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)